William Amos Snelling papers, 1873-1950
Emory University
William Amos Snelling papers, 1873-1950
Snelling, William Amos, 1856-1907.
Manuscript Collection No. 55
1.25 linear ft. (3 boxes)
Correspondence, poems, speeches, a diary, and clippings of Georgia educator and merchant William Amos Snelling.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Gift, 1970.
Restrictions on Access
Unrestricted access.
Biographical Note
William Amos Snelling (October 16, 1856 - May 25, 1907), a small businessman, Methodist layman and affectionate family man, spent most of his life in central Georgia. According to an obituary, William was about ten when his family - Richard Jackson and Lovicy Jane Snell Snelling and their three children Richard Jackson Jr., Mary ("Mollie") and William - moved from Florida to Washington County, Georgia. It was here, at Worthen's Store, they were living in 1873 when William left home to work in nearby Tennille. His parents, brother and sister soon migrated to Texas. William took a brief course at a commercial college in Baltimore during the summer of 1875 and taught school near Tennille during the summer of 1876 and 1877 while working in a local store at other times. In February 1878 he briefly opened a store of his own at Ball's Ferry on the Oconee River. The summer of 1879 again found him teaching school followed by a clerking job in Tennille in the fall. During these years in Tennille he occasionally contributed poems and other writings to the local newspaper. He accepted work with J. S. Wood Bro., cotton factors in Savannah beginning in September 1881. On December 28, 1882, William married Nannie Jackson Palmer (June 28, 1857 - April 8, 1950), the daughter of Dr. James Monroe and Sarah Jackson Palmer of Washington County. The couple lived in Savannah until the summer or fall of 1884 when they returned to Washington County and William apparently opened a general merchandise and cotton buying business at Sun Hill. Two years later he was again looking for work. In 1889 the family, which now included two daughters, moved to Macon where William worked for a wholesale grocery concern. Five more children were born to the Snellings before they moved in November, 1899, to Pinehurst, in Dooly County, Georgia and William again operated his own business. The Snellings remained in Pinehurst after William's death in 1907.
The Snelling children included three sons and four daughters: (1) Effie (1884-1970) who married G. W. Roberts; (2) Annie Mary "Mollie" (b. 1886), married James Augustus Whitehead; (3) William Amos Snelling, Jr. (b. 1889), married Bessie Reynolds; (4) James Palmer Snelling (1891-1965), married Edna Mozo; (5) Nannie (1893-1900); (6) Richard Jackson Snelling (b. 1896), married Erolyn Robbitt; and (7) Paula Snelling (b. 1899).
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence between William A. Snelling and Nannie Palmer before and after their marriage and letters from their numerous relatives comprise the bulk of this collection. Approximately 528 of the 647 letters, notes and postcards were written between 1874 and 1884. The letters reveal much of everyday life, telling of neighborhood events, church activities, house-hold chores, weddings and sickness, crops and business conditions, social activities and courtship customs of the time and occasional comments on current events. There are 283 letters sent by William to Nannie and 177 by Nannie to William. William's brother-in-law, Ferdinand Andler wrote 48 of the letters from Galveston, 1874-1877, discussing business conditions, prospects in the west, and contemporary issues. Other letters, notes and cards were written by the people listed below. The collection also includes miscellaneous family documents, poems and speeches some of which were written by William Snelling, and clippings of family obituaries.
Arrangement Note
Arranged in chronological order.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Andler, Ferdinand.; Harrison, John Gilmore.; Palmer family.; Snelling family.; Snelling, James Palmer, 1891-1965--Diaries.
Topical Terms
Methodist Church--Georgia.; World War, 1914-1918.
Geographic Names
Galveston (Tex.); Georgia--Agriculture.; Georgia--Economic conditions.; Georgia--Social life and customs.; Macon (Ga.).; Oconee (Ga.).; Pinehurst (Dooly County, Ga.).; Tennille (Ga.).; Washington County (Ga.).
Form/Genre Terms
Diary.; Poems.; Speeches.
Occupation
Merchant.
Container List
- Correspondence
- January 23, 1867 - May 5, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- June 22, 1874 - February 17, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- March 1, 1875 - August 16, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- September 3, 1875 - March 20, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- April 3, 1876 - July 31, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- August 2, 1877 - November 14, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- November 20, 1877 - January 28, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- February 11, 1878 - June 28, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- July 4, 1878 - March 27, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- April 16, 1879 - September 10, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- September 24, 1879 - December 21, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- January 7, 1880 - February 15, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- February 22, 1880 - April 27, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- May 4, 1880 - July 14, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- July 15, 1880 - September 30, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- October 3, 1880 - November 15, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- November 17, 1880 - December 31, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- January 6, 1881 - March 7, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- March 16, 1881 - April 28, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- May 3, 1881 - June 30, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- July 4, 1881 - August 28, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- September 7, 1881 - October 30, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- November 3, 1881 - December 20, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- January 1, 1882 - February 25, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- March 2, 1882 - May 30, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- June 5, 1882 - August 28, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- September 3, 1882 - October 30, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- November 2, 1882 - December 28, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- January 12, 1883 - July 13, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- July 16, 1883 - October 11, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- October 13, 1883 - December 31, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- 1884 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- 1885-1889 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- February 27, 1890 - July 19, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- April 16, 1895 - September 4, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- March 7, 1901 - August 1, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- December 22, 1922 - October 24, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- March 14, 1848 - February 19, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Other papers
- Family clippings (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Family documents (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Family history [parts of a diary and reminiscences] (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous poems and speeches (Box 3, Folder 8)